Guide to the Rice University postcard collection, 1913-1990s UA 246
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University postcard collection
1913-1990s
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 246
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
The collection consists of picture postcards featuring primarily buildings on the campus of Rice University in Houston, Texas. Included are scenes from as early as 1913 ranging to representations of buildings added to the campus in the 90's. There are also scenes documenting two nationally significant historical events that took place at Rice: President John F. Kennedy's 1961 speech calling for a manned moon landing, and the 1990 Economic Summit, which brought together eight international heads of state.
Biographical / Historical
Rice University opened as the William Marsh Rice Institute in 1912 on a 300-acre campus in Houston, Texas. At the beginning there were the administration building a residence hall, an academic building, and the mechanical lab and power plant, as well as an elaborate plan for additional buildings, all by the renowned Boston architectural firm of Cram, Goodhue, and Ferguson. Major growth took place after World War II, and in 1960 the name change from Institute to University acknowledged a broadened curriculum. As far as construction of new buildings is concerned, there have been several periods of growth: the late 40's, the late 50's, the 60's, the early 80's, the 90's and the first decade of the twenty-first century.
Postcards in the collection document two events of national historic significance that took place at Rice: President John F. Kennedy's 1961 speech calling for a manned landing on the moon, and the 1990 gathering of eight international heads of state for the Economic Summit.
Based on John B. Boles, "Rice University, Handbook of Texas Online (http://www. tsha online.org/handbook/articles/kbr05), accessed May 13, 2012. Published by the Texas State Historical Association.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of postcards featuring Rice Institute and Rice University, gathered from various sources. The largest segment is an album in which are mounted 35 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color scenes identified by the donor as the first cards made following the change of Rice's name from Institute to University. They were all made after July 1, 1960 and most in 1961. This album was a gift to Rice from Damon D. Hickey, class of 1964. The remainder of the collection consists of loose cards of varying sizes and dates. Most are 3-1/2" x 5-1/2", but the most recent are 4" x 6". The latter feature images of buildings "inside" contemporary graphic lettering. The smaller scenic cards have labels identifying buildings at either Rice Institute or Rice University. Three cards are not pictorial of Rice, two of which report a football score (Rice 7, A&M 6), and one which juxtaposes images of the mascots of Rice and the University of Texas. The date of the earliest card in the collection is identifiable by a 1913 postmark.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Items in this collection were donated by various individuals including Damon D. Hickey and Florence Stancliff.
Index Terms
Subjects
College buildings; Universities and colleges
Document Types
postcards
Places
Texas
- Series I. Album of 35 color picture postcards, 153122
  - Album of 35 color picture postcards, size 3-1/2" x 5-1/2"., 153123 (Box 1, Folder -)
    General
    Gift of Damon D. Hickey, member of the first class to enter Rice as Rice University 25 cards made between July 1, 1960, and end of 1961 10 cards made in 1964 and later
- Series II. Loose picture postcards, 153124
  - Accordion folder of 10 black and white photographs of campus scenes, marked "Bought in Houston in the Fall of 1954", 153125 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  - 16 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color picture postcards of Rice campus buildings, 153126 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  - 33 4" x 6" color postcards with buildings pictured "inside" contemporary graphic lettering, 19 for 9 of the colleges chronologically from Baker through Martel, and 14 for the University and 6 non-college buildings, 153127 (Box 1, Envelope 2)
  - 1 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcard picturing Allen Center, 153128 (Box 1, Envelope 2)
  - 1 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcard picturing Fondren Library, 153129 (Box 1, Envelope 2)
  - 11 postcards representing an historical range: 2 saying "7 – 6 Rice – A&M", 153130 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 1 1917 card picturing "Two mascots made famous by Texas A&M students" – a longhorn steer for the University of Texas and an owl for Rice Institute, 153131 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 1 color postcard of Rice football stadium filled to capacity with spectators and players, 153132 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 2 color postcards of the William Marsh Rice statue, 153133 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 1 color postcard of the main entrance gate of Rice, 153134 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 1 color postcard of the interior of the Grand Hall of the Rice Memorial Center, 153135 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 3 4" x 6" blue-gray and white postcards memorializing events in 1912, 1942, and 1962, 153136 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - 4 4" x 6" blue-gray and white postcards memorializing events in 1912, 1942, 1962, and 1990, 153137 (Box 1, Envelope 4)
  - 1 4" x 6" blue-gray and white postcard memorializing the 1990 Economic Summit of Industrialized Countries, 153138 (Box 1, Envelope 5)
  - 57 4" x 6" color postcards picturing the attendees of the 1990 Economic Summit in front of Lovett Hall, 153139 (Box 1, Envelope 5)
  - 24 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards picturing Rice campus scenes from 1914 through the 60's, collected by Florence Stancliff, class of '27, 153140 (Box 1, Envelope 6)
  - 3 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards showing aerial views of the Rice University campus, 153141 (Box 1, Envelope 7)
  - 18 color postcards and 4 black and white postcards of varying sizes, all picturing Lovett Hall over a wide range of dates, 153142 (Box 1, Envelope 8)
  - 11 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards picturing various residential college buildings, 153143 (Box 1, Envelope 9)
  - 7 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards picturing the Mechanical Laboratory, 153144 (Box 1, Envelope 10)
  - 10 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards picturing both exterior and interior views of the Rice Memorial Center, 153145 (Box 1, Envelope 11)
  - 3 3-1/2" x 5-1/2" color postcards picturing the Physics Building, 153146 (Box 1, Envelope 12)